<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ciuilitie of childehode with the discipline and institucion of children, distributed in small and compe[n]dious chapiters / and translated oute of French into Englysh, by Thomas Paynell.</title>
            <title>De civilitate morum puerilium. English. 1560</title>
            <author>Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1560</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00349</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10470.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2112</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23036441</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23036441</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26127</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00349)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26127)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1795:59)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ciuilitie of childehode with the discipline and institucion of children, distributed in small and compe[n]dious chapiters / and translated oute of French into Englysh, by Thomas Paynell.</title>
                  <title>De civilitate morum puerilium. English. 1560</title>
                  <author>Erasmus, Desiderius, d. 1536.</author>
                  <author>Paynell, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[110] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By John Tisdale, dwellynge in Knyghte Ryders strete, nye vnto the Quenes [m?]aredrop,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1560.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of Erasmus' "De civilitate morum puerilium"--Cf. STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and publisher from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁸ G⁷.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Pepys Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Etiquette, Medieval.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26127:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26127:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Ciui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litie of Childehode, with the diſcipline and inſtitucion of Children, diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted in ſmall and compe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Chapiters, and tranſlated oute of French into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſh, by Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell.</p>
            <p>Anno. Do. <hi>1560.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26127:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26127:2"/>
            <head>¶ To Mayſter Antonie Browne the So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne and Heyre of the righte Honorable Lord, Antonie Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Mountegue, Thomas Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel ſendeth greeting.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that I had Englyſhed thys Frenche boke incretyng very eligantly and compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly of the Ciuilitie and good maners of chyldehod and howe chyldren ſhould behaue them ſelues in the Church, at the Table, in the Scole, in the Chamber, after Dyner and Supper, in commen and pryuate Aſſembles, to honorable and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate perſones, to theyr Parents and Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemayſters, what Authours they ſhoulde rede, &amp; how to repete the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what raime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thei ſhould were, and howe to vſe it, what dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence they ſhulde vſe in theyre ſtudy and whan they ſhulde ſtudy, what ſemelye and manerly contenaunce of face geſture of hand and of the hole body ſhould become them, what recreation and paſtyme and what playes they ſhoulde vſe and refuſe, and wyth whom they ſhould playe, what
<pb facs="tcp:26127:3"/>they oughte to doe, or euer they prepare them ſelues to go to theyr reſte, and what thei ſhould afterwardes record &amp; imagine wyth manyfold other thynges very mete and neceſſarye for the educacion and eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of children. I wyth my ſelfe reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge and remembrynge how ruſticallye and rudely the chyldren of thys noble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme of Englande in moſte places be broughte up, beynge ignorant of all good maners, thought it no loſt time nor labor to tranſlate thys lytle booke in to Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe for the crudicion of chyldren, and to dedicate the ſame to you a chylde, and yet a ſpectacle to all chyldren of all good ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and pure maners where wyth ye doe manifeſtlye ſhewe where &amp; vnder whoſe wynge ye haue bene nouriſhed &amp; brought vppe, that vnder the ferula and wynge of your father, a lerned and a noble man, adurned wyth all humanite and vertue, wyth all ciuilitie &amp; godly behauiour, wyth wyſdome &amp; counſell, with affabilitie and comely geſture, wherfore it ſhalbe your parte from henceforth to enſue and folow the prudencie and wiſdome, the nobilyte and erudicion, the pure and exquiſyte ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb facs="tcp:26127:3"/>and the liberalite of your moſte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble father: for vnſemely it is the father to be ſerued, and the chylde vnterned, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be lyberal, and the chyld prodigal the father to be mylde and meke, and the chylde vngentle and churlyſhe, Therfore I woulde exhorte you in this your ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der age, to apply and to geue youre ſelfe to honor and to feare god, to erudicion &amp; vertue, to honor and to obeye youre pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes and elders, &amp; continually to ſerue God the geuer of al grace and goodnes, fo; ſo ſhall ye proſper both ſpiritually, and temporally, and obtaine the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour bothe of in nine, and of the immortall God for euer. Thus our Lorde encreaſe you and kepe you.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="instruction">
            <pb facs="tcp:26127:4"/>
            <head>¶ The Ciuilyte of Chyld<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hod foure principall poynts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to order and to inſtructe youthe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He office to order and to inſtruct youthe, hathe dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers pointes, of the which as this is the fyrſt. So it is the principal that the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſprite and mynde may be ſeaſoned wyth vertue. The ſeconde that he loue and learne lyberal artes. The thyrd, that he be inſtructed in the maners of doyng and actions the whych this lyfe requyreth. The fourth is, that at the begynnyng of hys age and yeares, he accuſtome hym ſelfe, vnto the Ciuilite of maners, the whyche thing I at this preſent haue pryncipally enterpriſed. For many other and we our ſelues al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo haue wrytten many thinges of the three other poynetes. And althoughe that the exterior and vtwarde geſture of the body dothe procede of the well
<pb facs="tcp:26127:4"/>lerned ſpyrite and mynde, yet we do ſee that ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tymes it chaunſyth throughe vncertain of the precepts y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome times we deſire thys good grace and gift in vertuous and wel lerned men. Nor I wyll not denye that thys is not the worſt part of philoſophy, but as mens iugements be now a dayes, it profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and ſerueth very muche to gette and to optayne beneuolence and amy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to cauſe the noble vertues of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule, to be commendable before the eyes of men.</p>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Modeſtye and ſimplicite is required to be in yonge chyldren.</head>
               <p>IT is neceſſary that in all thynge man be bothe of mynd, of body, of geſture and of raymente &amp; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, but ſpecialy handſom, modeſt &amp; ſimplicite becommeth yonge children, and among them and aboue, all other noble infants and chyldren. But they muſt be eſtemed more noble y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adurne theyr ſpirites wyth liberall ſtudies, then they which paynte in theyr ſcut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhons
<pb facs="tcp:26127:5"/>Lyons, Egles, Bulles and Liberds, they haue more true nobilitie in that place of ſo great blaſynge and armes maye take ſo much of the armes of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, as they haue receyued and ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of liberall artes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>The orberynge of the eyes.</head>
               <p>TO the intente than that the ſprite and mynde of the chylde well lerned maye ſhine on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſyde (it thyneth and is ſene principally in the face and viſage) his eyes muſt nedes be ſweete &amp; peaſable, ſhamefaſt and reſtfull, and not lifted vp or ouertwhart, the which is a ſigne of cruelnes, nor vage, nor fearefull, the whyche is a ſygne of folly, and a faulte of the brayne, nor ſquinrynge, nor blinekynge, the whyche appertain to them whych are ſuſpected and frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulently go about ſome treſon, nor to muche open and enlarged, the whyche appertainch to dullardes &amp; fooles, nor oftentymes twynkling, whych pertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be inconſtant, not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb facs="tcp:26127:5"/>hether and thether, the whych pertain to the aſtonied, for this was no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and blamed in Socrates, nor to ſharpe, the whych is a ſygne of anger, nor aſſygninge, and as it were apoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge and ſpekinge, the whyche is a ſigne of vnchaſtity, but declaring a cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tein quiet, temperat and amiable ſprit wyth all reuerence: and truly yt was not yll ſaide of the aunciente philoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, that the eyes be the leaſe of the ſoule. The auncient painters do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto vs, that in tymes paſt it was a ſinguler modeſtie to beholde the eyes halfe cloſed, as amonge certein Spanyardes, it is reputed gracious &amp; an amiable thinge to loke the eyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng abaſed and inclined. Like wiſe we learne by the forſaid paynters, that it was longe ſenſe a ſigne of a wiſe man to draw in and to cloſe the lippes, but that that is cumly of nature, ſhalbe eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temed goodly and honeſt before al peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, not wyth ſtandinge that in theſe things we muſt ſumtimes be like vnto fyſhes, the whiche dooe chaunge their couler after the thing they recounter
<pb facs="tcp:26127:6"/>and meete wyth all, ſo muſt we apply our ſelf after the cuſtome of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. There are beſide theſe other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. There are beſide theſe other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunces of the eyes that nature hath geuen to ſome after one ſorte, and to other after another ſorte, the whyche fall not vnder oure precepts, but that the euyl geſtures ofentimes do marre, not only the countenance and order of the eyes, but alſo of the hole body.</p>
               <p>Contrary wiſe the geſtures whyche are righte and conuenient cauſeth that thynge that is ſemely by nature to be more comely &amp; decent, &amp; that whych is vicious, yf they take them not away, wyll couer and diminiſhe them. It is nothyng beautifull to behold any man with one eye, for what other thing is that, but to make hym ſelfe one eyed. Let vs leue this geſture to the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes a people ſo called, &amp; to ſhoters, in croſſe-bowes, and to many other artificers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Streyght browes.</head>
               <p>THe Browes ought to be ſtreight and not drawne bakwards, the whyche is a ſigne of pride, nor exalted, the whiche is a ſigne of arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy:
<pb facs="tcp:26127:6"/>no hanginge vpon his eyes, the which pertaineth to dreamers and to thoſe that thinke euyll.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>A ioyfull and mery forehed.</head>
               <p>FOrther more let the forehed be ioyfull &amp; full, ſhewinge a good and mery chere, not wrincled &amp; reuen, the whiche pertaineth to age, not cumminge and goinge, for that pertaineth to hedge hogges, not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwarte and rughe, which thinge per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to bulles.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>A clene noſe.</head>
               <p>THat there be no ſneuill in the Noſe, the whych is a ſigne of a foule filthy people, and Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes the Philoſopher was blamid for this vice, to wipe his noſe with his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net if he haue one, or vpon his gowne is a ruſtical and a rude thing: to wipe his noſe with his arme or elbowe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to fyſhmongers, nor it is not more manierly to doo the ſame with
<pb facs="tcp:26127:7"/>his hand, if by and by thou make clene thy fingers vpon thy gowne. To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> filthines of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noſtrilles with an handkercher, is honeſte, and likewiſe to turne the body a litle if there be any honeſt men there, yf ther be any thing vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d after he hath wiped his noſe with two fingers, he muſt trede vpon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To blowe wyth the noſe and to ſnorce.</head>
               <p>TO blow lowde with the noſtrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les is a filthy thing, and a ſigne of color, and yet more filthy to ſnorte, the which pertaineth to thoſe that be furious and withoute vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge, yf they doo it cuſtomably, for they muſt be pardoned that haue a high brethe, and do brethe with great difficultie. To ſpeake in the noſe is a thinge that men mocke at, and it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to Storkes and Elephantes. To ſhrinke vp the noſe pertaineth to mockers, and to thoſe that playe the ſtorke backwardes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:7"/>
               <head>To Neſe.</head>
               <p>IF it chaunſe that thou muſt neſe in the preſence of ſum man, it is a point of ciuilite to turn thy ſelf a litle, and incontinente after that the violence ſhalbe appeaſed, to make the ſigne of the croſſe vpon thy mouthe, &amp; afterwardes puttinge of thy bonet to ſalute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaluted thee, or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaide, Chriſte helpe. For why to neſe as to yawne, doth wholy take away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eares. And afterwards to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre &amp; pray them not to be diſpleaſed, or els to geue them great thankes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ To ſaye God ſaue you when men neeſe.</head>
               <p>IT is a deuoute thing to ſay god ſaue the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whan he neſeth. If men doe it in the preſence of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers aged menne the whiche ſay vnto ſome honorable man or woman, God ſaue you the childe ought to put of his cappe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26127:8"/>
Forther more to enforce him ſelfe to neſe more lowder or to duble it to ſhew his force and ſtrengthe, pertaineth to thoſe that be glorious: and to retaine the ſowne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nature geueth, partaineth to foliſhe and vnapte people, the which praiſe ciuilitie more than helthe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Shamefaſt Chekes.</head>
               <p>THat the chekes be died with a certain natural ſhamefaſtnes &amp; with ſuche as is meete and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient for a noble infant w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge or falſe coleringe, but yet he muſt ſo temper it that it turne not in to great aſſuance or boldenes, nor that it bring not a certaine aſtoniſhemente and dulnes, and as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men prouerb doeth ſaye. The fourthe degre of foly. For ſome haue this nature ſo ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly emprented that it maketh them like to a parſon or ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ruleth. This vice is or may be moderate yf the childe do accuſtome him ſelf to lyue with men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be elder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſelf, and if he exerciſe him ſelf to play enterludes &amp; comedies.
<pb facs="tcp:26127:8"/>To cauſe the chekes to ſwell, is a ſigne of arrogance, and to cauſe them to faul and ſwage, dothe pertaine to him that diſconfort him ſelf, or is diſconfort, the one doth declare that the man is glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; proude, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is a traiter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>The mouth cloſe.</head>
               <p>LEt not the mouth be to much ſhut as his is that fereth to receiue the breth of another, nor y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it be open and gaping as foles haue, but that it be cloſe, the lippes kiſſing ech other ſwet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye. It is alſo a filthy &amp; a vile thinge of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes to put forth the lippes &amp; to do as if thou ſhouldſt cheriſh a horſſe with the tongue, although that this thinge is to be ſuffred in greate eſtates, that go thorow the midſte of a certaine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of people, for nothing miſbecum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth them, but we do order &amp; teach an infant.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To Yawne.</head>
               <p>IF by chaunce thou be enforſed to pawne, nor can not turne the, nor
<pb facs="tcp:26127:9"/>goe thy waies, thou muſte put before thy mouth, either thy napkin, or thy hande, and make the ſigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How one ſhould laugh, and how he ſhould not.</head>
               <p>TO laugh at all purpoſes, and at all thinges that we ſee done, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth pertaine to fooles. Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rywiſe, to laugh, at nothing that men doe, doth pertaine to ſadde men and to ſhepiſh perſons. It is an ewil, thing to laughe at vile and diſhoneſt thinges. Morcouer one maner of laughinge, &amp; to make a great laughter that moueth all the bodie, whereof the Greekes cal it al mouing and trauailing is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent nor mete for no age, ſo than it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not become youth.</p>
               <p>It to alſo a filthy thing whan a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laugheth to neye like a horſe, nor that laughter is not very goodly that eular geth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth, &amp; cauſeth the cheekes as it were to retere, and diſcouereth the teeth, the which laughter is called the girning of a dogge. No man ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
<pb facs="tcp:26127:9"/>his ioye in ſuche maner, to the ende that he ſhew not a diſſolute ſprit, and that he deforme not his mouthe.</p>
               <p>Theſe bee the woordes of fooles, I piſſe thorow laughter, I burſt thorow laughter, I thought I ſhould haue dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through laughter: or, I ſounde tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row laughter. If anye thing chaunce, where at a man doth ſo laugh, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth hun to eate again y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, he muſt couer his face eyther with his napkin, or with his hande. To laugh all alone, or without any euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cauſe, is attributed to fooliſhnes. But yet if it ſo chaunce, it ſhall be ciuilly &amp; well done, to declare the cauſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he laughed: or if it be not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueled, he muſt finde ſome thing, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende that no man thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they mocke hint.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To byte the lyppe.</head>
               <p>TO bite the nether lippe is vile &amp; diſhoneſt, for it is the geſture of a man that threatneth, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe to bite the vpper lippe. And alſo
<pb facs="tcp:26127:10"/>to licke the borders of his lyppes is an vncomely thing. To haue the lyppes extended, and as preſt and redy to kiſſe one, hath bene of long time a gracious and a comelye thing amonge the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, as their paintinges &amp; pictures declare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of drawing and putting ouce the toungue.</head>
               <p>HE mocketh ſome manne that draweth out his tonge at him, theſe ſnatchers &amp; gapers ſhould vſe and do that.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To ſpitte.</head>
               <p>WHan thou ſpitteſt turne thy face aſide, to thintent thou ſpit vpon no man. If thou haue caſte anye ordure or filthineſſe vpon the ground, thou muſt trede it out with thy fote as I haue ſaide already, to the ende that it trouble no mans heart nor ſtomake. If it be not lawfull for to turne thee, receiue and gather thy ſpittle into thy
<pb facs="tcp:26127:10"/>handkercher. It is a vile thing to ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low downe thy ſpittle, as we dooe ſee ſome that ſpit at euery woorde, not of neceſſity, but by cuſtom. Furthermore there be ſom that doe coughe, and that by a vſuall cuſtome, ſuch maner of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doth ſmel and declare a liar, or one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpeaking, doth forge what he ſhould ſay.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To belche.</head>
               <p>OTher at euery worde doe belche with leſſe honeſtie, the whiche thing if it come and drawe to a cuſtome in youthe, it will continue in age. The ſelfeſame muſt bee iudged of coughing, wherof Clitipho in Tere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was reprehended of a ſeruant. If thou be conſtrained to coughe, be ware thou do it not before the mouth or face of a nother, and that there bee not a fonde maner to coughe hier than nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To vomite.</head>
               <p>IF y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wilt vomit, turne thy ſelf to ſoe other place, for why to vomit is not ill of it ſelfe, but it is a
<pb facs="tcp:26127:11"/>vile thinge, if gluttonie bee the cauſe therof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Cleane teeth.</head>
               <p>YOuthe muſt take hede that theyr teeth be cleane, but to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> white with pouder, belongeth to maidens, to rub them with ſalte or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, is euil for the gummes, to do this with his vrine, belongeth to Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yardes, if any thing remaine betwene thy teethe, thou muſt not take it out w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> thy knife, nor with thy nailes, as dogs and cattes doe, nor with thy napkin, but with a tooth piker made of a ſpin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, or with a quill, or with the lyttle bones taken out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpurres of cockes or capons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To waſhe the mouthe.</head>
               <p>IT is an honeſte thing &amp; a whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to waſhe the mouth in the morninge, with cleane and pure water, but to returne often tymes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it is fooliſhnes, and vncomelyneſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:26127:11"/>Of the vſe of the tonge we ſhal ſpeake in his place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of a cleane head.</head>
               <p>IT is a ruſtical and a rude thyng not to be combe: and that ther be a clenlynes, but not a tyremente of maidens. There muſt be neither lice nor nittes. Often times to ſcratche the head in the preſence of other is a thing not very dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nor honeſt: as to ſcratch the body with the nailes, is a foule &amp; a filthy thyng, and ſpecially if it be done by a cuſtome and not of neceſſitie.</p>
               <p>That the heere fal nor hange not v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his eies, nor vpon his ſhoulders. Oftentimes to couer his buſhe by ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng and caſting vp of the head, doeth pertain to horſes that bee pompeous &amp; proude. With the hande to turne vp y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heere from the forehead an hygh, is a thyng not very faire nor comely: but to ſhede them with the hand is more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>An upright bodye.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:12"/>
               <p>TO holde down the heade and to lift vp the ſhoulders, is a ſigne of ſlouthfulnes. To bowe backe the body, is a token of arreganey: but to kepe it vpright without enforceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is comely. That the head neither hang to the one ſide nor to the other, for that ſmelleth of an hipocrite: excepte there be a cauſe that a man may holde it ſo, or that ſome like thing require it. Ye muſt gouerne and rule your ſhoulders with a iuſte counterpeſe, and not after the maner of the Atheniens, to holde vp the one, and to let faule the other. For ſuch maner of countenaunces are diſpraiſed in litle children tournynge themſelfe into nature, difformynge and defilynge all the bodye contrarye to his nature. And therefore they that of ſluggiſhneſſe haue taken a cuſtome to crooke the bodye, ſhall get a crooked backe and a vice that nature hath not geuen them: and they that haue a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to hange the heade on the one ſyde, ſhall ſo harden and geue them to that vſe and maner, that whan thei bee greate, they cannot chaunge it.
<pb facs="tcp:26127:12"/>The tender bodies bee lyke younge plantes, tho whiche growe and ware harde in ſuche ſorte as thou haſt bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and drawne them with ſtake, corde, and bande. To caſte the armes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde the backe, betokeneth an ydle perſone and a theſe: nor it is not much better ſittinge or ſtandinge to holde or to ſet one hande vppon his ſide, the whiche thinge neuertheleſſe to ſome menne ſemeth faire and goodlye, and to ſmell of a manne of warre. All that that pleaſeth fooles, is not yet honeſt, but that thynge that is after reaſone and nature. The reſte ſhall bee ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken whan wee ſhall come to ſpeake of deuices and purpoſes, and alſo of the Table.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Vnhoneſt members to bee coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</head>
               <p>DO diſcouer wout neceſitie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, vnto the which nature hath geuen ſhame, oughte to bee euyll to
<pb facs="tcp:26127:13"/>an honeſt childe. And whan neceſſitye conſtraineth him, he oughte to dooe it with a certaine decent ſhamefaſtneſſe: ye and that he haue no witneſſe to ſee them. For the Aungels are alwayes preſent vnto whom ſhamefaſt compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and keping of chaſtity is very grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for yong children. And therfore we muſte ſo muche the leſſe ſuffer other to touch our me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which to turn our eyes, is chaſtitie and honeſtie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To retayne vrine or ventoſitye.</head>
               <p>TO retayne vrine is hurtfull to healthe, but to make it ſecretely, is a thing that kepeth hym from ſhame. There be that commaund that a childe ſhould retayne the ventoſitye of the belly, beholding of his buttocks together, but ceries this is not a point of Ciuilitie to ſhewe himſelf gracious and of good maners, and to engender a certain ſickenes, yf it bee lawfull to turne away, and beyng al alone to let it goe, and auoide it: otherwyſe after
<pb facs="tcp:26127:13"/>the auncient &amp; olde prouerbe, he muſte diſguiſe the ſo unde by coughyng, they ſhoulde haue forbidden all this at once not to diſcharge the belly, conſideryng that it is more dangerous to kepe and holde his wynde, than to retayne hys vrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Howe one ſhould ſit and ſtande vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryghte.</head>
               <p>TO ſit with the knees open, and caſte abrode or holde his legges wyde or crooked, doeth pertayne to thoſe that be braue, and dooe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfaite gentlemen. Whan thou ſhalt be ſet, ſee that thy knees and thy feete be cloſe together, alſo when thou doeſt ſtande, that at the leaſt thei be meane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly open. Some doe ſit after this ſorte, that they cauſe the one legge to hange aboue the knee. Some other ſtand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, hauing their armes a croſſe, and their legges together, the one maner pertaineth to men that be penſyfe: the other to people that be foolyſhe, and to
<pb facs="tcp:26127:14"/>ſit caſtynge one foote vppon the lefte thighe, is the moode and maner of au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciente kynges, but it is reproued.</p>
               <p>In Italie certaine menne for honor ſake doe laie one foote vppon another, nor they ſuſtayne not themſelues but as it were vppon one legge, after the maner of ſtorkes, if this geſture be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient for litle children, I know not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To encline to doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence and make courteſye.</head>
               <p>LIkewiſe to encline and bowe thy knees after one maner is wel ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, in ſome countrey, it is miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyked, and another in another. Some doe bowe the knees together, and ſom holde them righte vp: and other ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what crooked. There be that eſteme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that maner pertayneth to women: and therfore kepyng their bodies vpright, they firſte bowe the right knee, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent after the left, the which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is praiſed in the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d The Frenche men do bowe onely the
<pb facs="tcp:26127:14"/>right knee with a certayne ſwete tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and mouing of the body. In lyke thinges diuerſitie hath no repugnance againſt honeſtie. It ſhall be in the wyl of eche one, either to vſe the maners of the countrey, or to cleue to the maners of ſtraungers, foraſmuche as there bee men, vnto whom the thynges and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of ſtraungers are moſt pleaſant.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of goynge.</head>
               <p>THat our going be not as it wer broken and fayned, nor to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtye: the one pertaineth to ſofte and effemenate perſones, the other to thoſe that be furious and mad. Likewiſe that it be not wauering fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one ſide to the other, and therefore let vs leaue it to the menne of warre of Swicherlande, and to thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eſteme it a great ornament to weare fethers in their bonets. There are ſome y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue a fooliſhe maner of haltyng whan they gooe. Notwithſtandynge that wee haue ſeene Buſhoppes that glorifyed in ſuche maner of goynge.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26127:15"/>
To ſhake the legges when men do ſyt pertayneth to fooles, as to fyddle and to make a thouſande toyes with the handes, is a ſygne of an vnſounde and entire vnderſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of rayment and of the honeſt forme and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the ſame.</head>
               <p>WE haue ſpoken compendiouſlye and briefly of the body. Now we ſhall ſpeake of the raymente in fewe woordes: becauſe that the raime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in a maner is the body of the body, and becauſe that thereby a man maye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture, and geue iudgement of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and qualitie of the ſpirite &amp; minde of men. Notwithſtanding that we can not preſcribe nor limit a certayne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and faſhion, becauſe the fortune, ryches, or greate dignitie of euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not like: and that in all nacions lyke thynges are not ſemely or vnſemelye. Furthermore becauſe the ſelfe ſame thynges pleaſe not at all times, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe: therfore as in other things, like
<pb facs="tcp:26127:15"/>wyſe in this we muſt geue ſomewhat as the prouerbe ſaith, to the lawe, and to the place. And furthermore wiſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commaunde to ſerue the tyme, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe in theſe varieties me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> finde a thyng that is of it ſelfe honeſt or not honeſt, as thynges that ſerue to no vſe for the whiche garmentes are made.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Long tayles or traynes in womens gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</head>
               <p>MEn doe deride and mocke to ſee women drawe their long tailes after them, and men alſo be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, whether thei be conueniente and meete for Cardinals and Buſhops, let other men iudge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Shorte gownes.</head>
               <p>VEry ſhorte gownes haue bene euermore vituperated and bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as well in men as in wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: for why the ſeconde vſe of gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes is to couer ſuche partes as can
<pb facs="tcp:26127:16"/>not honeſtly be ſhewed to the eyes of men. It is ſaide already not to pertain to man, and alſo to ſauer the feminine ſepe to be vngyrded: but nowe a dayes it is no rebuke nor vice to no man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſhamefull partes are couered with the ſherte and hoſen, although y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gowne doth open it ſelfe, and flyeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode with the winde. For thys cauſe the garment is vnhoneſt among al peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, the whiche is ſo ſhorte, that whan thou ſtoupeſte downe, it couereth not thoſe partes, the whiche men do couer for honor ſake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To Iagge and to cut garmentes.</head>
               <p>TO cut &amp; iagge his raiment, thei do it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are out of their wit and mad.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Painted and garded rayment.</head>
               <p>TO vſe painted and garded raime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pertaineth to fooles and apes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:16"/>
               <head>Clenlines in ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</head>
               <p>IT muſte be then, that there be cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines in rayment after the riches and dignitie of man, and after the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and cuſtome: and that the garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bee not vituperable to the crafteſman, nor ſettyng forth a moleſtiouſnes and arrogancie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Modeſtie in gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</head>
               <p>TO younge children belongeth a garment that is not curious, ſo it be without foulnes &amp; filthines</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Clenlineſſe and honeſtie in the vſe and parte of them.</head>
               <p>THere be certain that make redde the borders of their ſhertes and of their coates with a certain per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fume of vrine, or els thei plaiſter their breſtes, and their ſleues with a certayn vile couering, and not with playſter, but with the ſneuil &amp; filthines of their noſes, &amp; with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordure &amp; ſpittle of their mouth. So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ther be whoſe gown dothe ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge all on one ſide, vnto other it doth fal backwards vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reines of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> back
<pb facs="tcp:26127:17"/>and there bee vnto whom that ſemeth verye faire and goodlye. So that al the garmentes of the body muſt be cleane, proper, and well faſhioned, likewyſe thei muſt be after the proporcion of the body. If thy parentes haue geuen thee any ioly and ſemely apparell, beholde it not tourningre thy eyes vnto it, nor make not as though thou were merye and well contente, ſhewyng it vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for one of theſe maners pertaine to apes, and the other to pecockes. Let other men looke vpon thee, and bee thou ignoraunt that thou arte in good order. The more that a great mannes riches is, the more is his modeſtie and humilitie agreable. It is for the poore whom we muſte ſuffer moderatelye to glorifie themſelues, to the comforte of their pouertie. But the riche man ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing foorth the ſumptuouſnes of hys raiment, doeth reproche other of theyr miſery, &amp; purchaſeth to himſelfe enuy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:17"/>
               <head>¶ Howe he ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue himſelfe in the Churche.</head>
               <p>AT all times and as ofte as thou doeſt come into the churche, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer thy head, and ſwetely bow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng thy knees, ſalute Ieſus Chriſte. Loke that thou come into no churche, but with lyke deuocion, thy head be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bare, and both thy knees vpon the earth, make thy praier to almightye god diſpoſing al thy body to deuocion, and thinking y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god is preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable milions of Aungels. And if he that doth come to ſpeake to a king being in the companye of his nobilitie not diſcouering hys head, is of all men eſtemed not onely rude, but out of his wit: what is he that hath his head vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, and his knees vp right there, where the immortall king of kynges, and the geuer of immortalitie is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with al his celeſtial ſpirites, moſt reuerently about him: nor thou nedeſt not to care if thou ſe him not, for other eyes ſee him, and as certain it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as if thou ſaweſt them with thy corporall eyes, for the eyes of faith ſee more certainly, then the eyes of the fleſhe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:18"/>
               <head>¶ Not to walke in the Churche.</head>
               <p>ALſo it is an vndecent thing and an vnhoneſte to walke in the churche, and to counterfeit the Peripatiques, that is to ſay, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotles ſcholers, the which wer wont to walke whan thei diſputed. Certes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pallas, towne houſe, porches, haules, and market places are conueniente for a man to walke in, and not the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the whiche are dedicated for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſermons, for the ſacramentes, &amp; for praiers and oracions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Beholde and heare the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher diligentlye.</head>
               <p>THat the eyes beholde the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and that the eares be atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, that the minde and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heart take hede with greate deſire and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, and with reuerence not although thou diddeſt heare a man, but god ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto thee by the mouth of a man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:18"/>
               <head>Whan one ſhould ſtande upright or knele in the communion tyme.</head>
               <p>WHan any man doth rede or ſinge the ghoſpell, ſtande vp, &amp; yf thou maiſt, hearken vnto it deuoutly. Whan thei ſinge the Simbole, that is to ſaie, Credo in vnum deum. &amp;c. the Crede, and at theſe woordes, et homo factus eſt, he was made man, kneele downe, humbling thy ſelfe at the leaſt in this point, for the honor of him that being aboue all the heauens, hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed himſelf vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth for thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion. Whan all thy body is diſpoſed to deuocion, turne thy face, &amp; thy heart to god.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>An vndecent maner of knelyng.</head>
               <p>TO touch, the grounde with one knee and to holde the other vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, vpon the whiche the lefte arme doth reſte, is the geſture &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce of an euyl man of warre, the which mocking our Lorde, ſaid: I ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute thee king of the Iewes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26127:19"/>
Therfore ſet downe both thy knees, &amp; ſomewhat abaſe all the reſte of thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy with a certaine veneracion and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of honor.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ What he ſhould doe in the churche whan there is no communion.</head>
               <p>AL the reſidue of time, either rede ſomewhat oute of ſome booke of praiers, or els of holye Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or els that thy ſpirit be thinking or contemplating vpon ſome celeſtiall thing, or vpon god.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Neyther to bable nor to turne thyne eyes hether and the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the churche.</head>
               <p>TO bable or then to deuiſe wyth him that ſitteth by thee, dooeth pertaine to thoſe that beleue not that god is preſent. To caſt &amp; to turne the eyes hether and thether, doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to thoſe that be out of their wyt. Eſteme that thou art gone to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church
<pb facs="tcp:26127:19"/>in vain, if thou returne not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence better, more pure and cleane.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the Table and howe a childe oughte to vſe and behaue hymſelfe.</head>
               <p>FIrſt or euer thou ſit down at the Table waſh thy handes, &amp; pare thy nailes. At the Table thou muſte ſhewe a certaine cherefulnes, to auoid diſſolute babling. Sit not doune vntill thou haue waſhte, and that thy nayles be firſt pared, leſt there remayn any filthines, and leſſe thou bee called extreme filthy and proud.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ To make water or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he ſytte down.</head>
               <p>HE muſte before he ſitte downe make water, or diſcharge hys belly if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing require it. And if peraduenture it chance that thou be to much preſſed it ſhalbe wel done firſt to vnloſe thy poyntes, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſhouldeſt dooe it with leſſe honeſtye at
<pb facs="tcp:26127:20"/>the Table.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To bee ioyfull and mery at the table.</head>
               <p>AND wiping thy handes, caſte by and by awan all moleſtiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and heauineſſe that thou haſt in thy hearte, for thou muſte not bee heauie at the Table, nor make none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man ſad nor heauie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To bleſſe and ſaye grace and how.</head>
               <p>IF anye manne commaunde thee to ſaye grace, prepare thy face &amp; thy handes to deuocion, lokynge vpon the moſt honeſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſiſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and naming Ieſus bowe thy knee, yf this bee geuen and appointed to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hearken and aunſwere with like deuocion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:20"/>
               <head>Humilitie at the Table.</head>
               <p>GEne quietly the higheſt rowme to another, and beeing inuited to aſcende more higher, humbly excuſe thy ſelfe: but if any man of auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie doe diuers times and in good earneſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande thee, obey him with ſhamefaſtneſſe, to the ende that thou ſeme not to be opinatiue in place to be eiuill and well manerd.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>The countenaunce of armes &amp; handes.</head>
               <p>BEyng ſette holde both thy han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des vpon the Table, not ioyned together, nor vpon thy trencher: for there are ſome that fooliſh lye dooe holde the one or bothe in their boſom. To leane with one elbow or with both vpon the Table, is graunted to thoſe that throughe age and ſickenes are fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: and thou muſte diſſemble the like, but not folow in this certaine delicate courchers, the whiche do thynke, that all that thei doe becommeth them. In the meane whyle thou muſte take hede that thou hurte no manne with thy elbowe, nor that thou puſhe nor thruſt him that is next thee, and that wyth
<pb facs="tcp:26127:21"/>thy feete thou ſmite them not, that are on the other ſide of the table.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The countenaunce beying ſette in chayre, or in any other place.</head>
               <p>TO moue hymſelfe in his chayre, and to ſitte nowe vppon the one thigh, and nowe vpon the other, is like vnto a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſtroke for ſtroke doth loſe his belly, or that laboreth to loſe it. And therfore the body muſte be kept vpright with a iuſt meaſure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Vpon which arme we ought to hold and beare the nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyn, and whan it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient &amp; mete to eate bare hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded or coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</head>
               <p>IF thei geue thee a napkine, laye it vppon thi lefte arme. If thou take thy repaſt with greate and noble men, loke that thy head be well
<pb facs="tcp:26127:21"/>combe, put of thy bonet, except the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the countrey be otherwyſe, or that the aucthoritie of ſome doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde thee the contrary, vnto whom it were no honeſtie to diſobey.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Whan a childe ſhoulde ſitte at the table, and whan he ſhoulde not.</head>
               <p>THei haue in ſome place euen of cuſtome that the children ſhall eate at the ende of the table bare headed, he muſt not ſet hymſelfe, but whan he is commaunded, nor he ſhall not tary there to the latter ende of the repaſt: but whan he hath eaten ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, taking away his trenchour, and bowinge his knee, he muſte doe reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence principatly vnto hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is moſte honorable among the aſſiſtence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Glaſſe and knyfe.</head>
               <p>THe glaſſe and the knife beynge cleane muſt be layde vppon the right ſide, and the bread on the
<pb facs="tcp:26127:22"/>left. Cut breade with a knife, and eate it with reuerence. Leaue of for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licatenes of certain courchers the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and vſe to breake the bread with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> endes of thy ſingers, laying thy hande vpon it. As concerning thy ſelfe, cut it gentlemanly with thy knife, not cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the cruſte rounde aboute aboue and beneath, for that doth ſauer a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Our elders in al repaſtes did eate bread with great reuerence as a holy thing: and of that commeth the cuſtome of this time, to kiſſe the bred, yf perchaunce it bee fallen vppon the grounde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Whan, howe, what, and howe muche a chyld ought to drink at his repaſte.</head>
               <p>BI and by to begin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> repaſte with drink is for drunkardes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> drink not for any thirſte, but by a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome: nor it is not onely a diſhoneſtie, but alſo a great noiaunce of the health of the body. He muſt not drinke incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent after he hath ſupt vp and eaten his porage, &amp; yet leſſe, whan he hathe
<pb facs="tcp:26127:22"/>eaten milk. It is neither helthſom nor honeſt for a child to drink aboue twyſe at one repaſt, or at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt thryſe. That he drinke once whan he hathe eaten a while of the ſecond meſſe, and ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whan he is drie, furthermore about the ende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> repaſt, he drinking muſte drinke genely &amp; ſwetely, not glutting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nor blowyng as horſes doe. The wine and beere that maketh one dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as much as wine, as thei doe hurt the health of children, ſo they dooe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame and diſhonor them. Water is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient for the age that is hote: but yf the nature of the countrey, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth not ſuffer him to drink it, let him vſe ſmall bere, or ſom wyne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is not burning, &amp; that it be wel tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered with water. Or els here are the retribucion &amp; rewardes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> folow thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loue wine. Yelow teeth, &amp; as it were ruſly, hanging cheekes, blered eyes, a dulnes of vnderſtanding, &amp; to be ſhort, age before age, &amp; before his time. Swa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low down thy morſels or euer y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> drink nor com not nie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glaſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy mouth, before thou haſt wiped it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thi napkin
<pb facs="tcp:26127:23"/>ſpecially if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offer thee his glaſſe or if men drinke in a common cuppe. It is a filthy thyng to looke aſyde wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou art drinking, ſo it is a diſhoneſte thing to turne thy head vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy backe, after the maner of ſtorkes, for feare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ſhould remayne any thing in the goblet. Thanke hym ſwetely that ſhal praye thee to drynke, and in takyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> glaſſe, and in taſting it a litle, fain thy ſelfe to drinke wiſely, as thoughe thou were not a thirſt, and this ſhall bee y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for hym that diſſembleth &amp; can plaie the courcher, and he ſhal promiſe to make an ende, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he waxeth grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yf he that did drinke vnto hym bee ſo rude, that he conſtrainde hym there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Modeſtie at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng to the table.</head>
               <p>THere be that ſcantly can tarye till thei be wel ſet to eate theyr meate, and this pertaineth to wolues, &amp; to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can ſcacely tarie till the meate be taken out of the pot. By the meanes wherof thou ſhalt
<pb facs="tcp:26127:23"/>neuer put thy hand firſt into the diſhe, nor that onely for this cauſe that it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth thee to be a glutto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; famiſhed, but alſo becauſe there is oftentymes daunger therein: for he that hath putte whote meate in his mouthe, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to caſte it out agayne, or to burne his tonge if he ſwalowe it downe, ſo it foloweth that one or other doth mocke hym, with the euyll that he hath ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ To moderate his appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, and to auoide lykeryſhnes.</head>
               <p>MEn muſte tarye a certayn time, to the intent that the child lerne to moderate his appetite. To y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which intencion Socrates being now very olde, woulde neuer drinke of the firſt cuppe. If the chyld be ſet with his ſupertours, that he put his hande laſte into the diſh, nor that he doe it not, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he be firſt commaunded. To tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and to put his fingers in ſawees, caudelles, or brotthes, pertayneth to rude and thoſe that be broughte vp in
<pb facs="tcp:26127:24"/>villages: and therefore they muſte take the thynge that thei will haue wyth a knife, without choſyng it in the dyſhe, as they doe that are likerythe, but he muſt take that, that by chaunce is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hym. The whiche faſhion: nay be learned of Homere, the whiche dooeth often times ſpeake thus. Thei boldely put to their handes vnto the meat y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſet before them. Likewiſe yf that, that is before the child be an exquiſite mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, he muſt leaue it for another, and take the nexte. So than as this is the dede of a likeriſh perſon, to trayne his hande on euerye ſide of the diſhe, ſo in like maner it is ſcacely honeſt to turne the dithe that the beſte morſelles maye come towardes thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To receiue the thing that is preſented with ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilitye.</head>
               <p>IF any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geue thee a good mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, after that thou haſte excuſed thee, receiue it, but whan thou haſt cut a certain porcion for thy ſelfe, reſtore the reſt to him that gaue it thee
<pb facs="tcp:26127:24"/>or geue part to hym that is nexte vnto thee. That thing that cannot be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the fingers, muſt be receiued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the trencher. If any man geue thee of a tarte, or of a paſty, receiue it with thy trencher. If the thyng that is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee be liquide and fleting take it, and after that the ſawcer be wiped &amp; made cleane with a napkin reſtore it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To licke his fingers, or to wype them vpon his gowne.</head>
               <p>ALſo it is an vnciuill thyng to lick his fingers, or to wipe them vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his gowne: and ſodainly to ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe downe hole morſelles dothe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to ſtorkes or to gapers. If there be any that doth cutte or carue, it is an vnmanerly thinge to offer or to putte forth thy hande or thy trencher before he proffer thee any thing: for it ſemeth that thou wouldeſte take that awaye, that is prepared for another. Thou muſte receyue that is preſented and geuen</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:25"/>
               <head>To caſte honeſtly awaye that a manne wyll not ſwalow.</head>
               <p>IF perchaunce thou haſt taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that is not good to ſwa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low, turning thy face to ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part, eiect it. To take again the meate that is halfe eaten, or the bones that are laid apart vpon the trencher, is blamed. Beware thou caſte not the refuſe of thy trencher vnder the table, leſt thou defile the place or to lay them vpon the table clothe, nor within the platter, but to ſeperate and laye them on one of the corners of thy trencher, or put them into the ſawcer, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche in ſome places thei doe geue expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to put in the refuſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To make cleane the ſhell of an egge.</head>
               <p>TO make clene y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhell of an egge with thy fingers is a rediculous and a thing that men laughe at: &amp; to dooe it putting thy tong into it, is yet more rediculous. It is doone more properly with thy knife.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:25"/>
               <head>To gnawe bones.</head>
               <p>TO gnawe bones doth pertaine to dogges, to make them clene with a knife is a ciuill thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To take ſalte with a knife.</head>
               <p>MEn doe count by a common pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb, thre fingers put w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſalt celler, to be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> armes of villains. Ye muſt take with a knife aſmuch ſalt as ye haue nede of. If the ſalte ſeller be to farre of, thou putting foorth thy tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cher muſt aſke it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To licke the diſhe.</head>
               <p>TO licke the diſhe with thy tong, or thy trencher wher ſuger was or ſome other likeriſhe thinge, doeth pertain to cattes, and not to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:26"/>
               <head>To cutte meate in ſmall mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelles, and to chamme it well, or euer thou ſwalowe it.</head>
               <p>THat the childe doe cut his meat in ſmall morſels vpon his tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and that incontimently he do put bread vnto it, wel cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med before he ſende it to the ſtomake: for this thing dooeth not onely profite vnto honeſtie, but alſo to the health of the body. There be that for a truth doe rather deuoure, and as gluttons dooe ſwalow than eate, &amp; euen ſo as though a man ſhould cary them and bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to priſon. Suche gredines is like vnto them that ſtele and rob the thyng that thei doe eate. There be that at once do put ſo muche in their mouthes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr chekes be blowne vp and ſwell on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide like beaſtes: other do open their iawes ſo wide whan they eate, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they make a noiſe as it wer hogges. Other through a feruente heate to eate, dooe blowe with their noſtrelles as though they ſhould be ſtrangled.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:26"/>
               <head>Nother to drinke nor to ſpeake hauyng thy mouth full.</head>
               <p>TO drinke or to ſpeake wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ones mouth is full, is neither honeſt nor yet withoute daunger. It muſt nedes bee that the good purpoſes ſpoken one after the other muſt in the meane ſpace breake the continuall ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To maintayne honeſte geſture in eatynge.</head>
               <p>THere be that continually do dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nke and eate, nor y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> becauſe they coulde not otherwiſe maintayne theyr geſtures, yf they ſcratched not their beds, if thei piked not their teeth, if thei made not ſome toyes with their handes, if they plaide not with their kniues, if thei cought not, yf they ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not. Suche maner of doynges pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede of a ruſtical ſhame and behauiour like vnto folye. We muſte paſſe ouer this moleſtiouſnes and geue hede and harken to other mens deuices, if opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie do not ſuffer vs to ſpeake.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:27"/>
               <head>Not to be penſifull and heauye at the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</head>
               <p>IT is vnſemely and an vnmaner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thing to ſit at the table as pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſife and heauy. Ye ſhall ſee ſome ſo fooliſh and ſo dreaming y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei heare not what other men ſaie, nor fele not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei eate, and if ye call them by their name, thei ſeeme to bee awaked from ſome great ſleepe, their heartes are ſo muche ſet vpon eating.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Not to behold what ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man doth eate.</head>
               <p>IT is a diſhoneſtie to turne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eies about the table, to ſee what eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry manne eateth: nor he muſt not holde nor looke long vpon anye of the aſſiſtence. And it is furthermore more diſhoneſt to beholde with the corner of the eie thoſe that bee on euerye ſide of thee. It is a very honeſt thing turning of the necke to beholde the thinge that men doe at another table.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:27"/>
               <head>Not to report the thynge that hath bene free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken at the Table.</head>
               <p>IT is not faire nor honeſt, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye for a childe, but alſo for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to reporte any thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hathe bene frely ſpoken or done at the table.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Modeſtie in ſpeakynge and laughyng.</head>
               <p>WHan the childe ſhal drink or eate with his ſuperiours, he ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſpeake, if neceſſitie conſtrain him not, or if he be not inuited of ſome manne to ſpeake. That he ſmile moſte ſwetely at thoſe thinges that ſhall bee ſpoken merely. That he neuer laughe at filthy and vile wordes, but frowne, if he that ſpake thoſe wordes by a man of dignitie, &amp; make as though he harde them not, nor vnderſtode them. Sile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce doth bring honor to women, but more to litle children. Some do anſwere, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that he whiche ſpeaketh to them hath made an ende of his purpoſe: and therfore it bappeneth often times that he which doth anſwer is ſcorned, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he geueth place to the aunciente pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe. Thou reenters the pykes, that is: y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> aunſwereth nothinge to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> matter.
<pb facs="tcp:26127:28"/>The great and very wiſe king dooeth teache vs this, and dooeth attribute to foly to aunſwer before thou haſt heard and certes he heareth not at all, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doth not vnderſtande him that ſpeketh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: therefore let him hold his peace for a while, vntill he repete of hymſelf the thing that he hath ſpoken, But yf he wil not, but dothe preſſe him to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> child ſhal pray him moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to pardon him, and that it woulde pleaſe him to repete againe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hathe ſpoken. Whan he hathe vnderſtanded the demaunde and queſtion, he muſt a litle bethinke himſelfe, and than aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere him briefly and ioyfully.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Not to trouble the good chere with moleſtious wordes.</head>
               <p>WE muſte ſpeake nothing at the Table, that ſhall trouble y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good chere. To touch the good name of any manne is a very euill dede. Nor he muſte not renue his heauines to no man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:28"/>
               <head>Blame not the meates that be preſente, nor praiſe them not to muche that be preſented.</head>
               <p>TO blame the meates that be ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the table, is eſtemed an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuill and an vnmanerly thing, nor it pleſeth not him that receued you to his diner. If the thinges be thyne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the banket is made of, as it is a cyuyll thing to excuſe the ſmall preparacion and entreating, ſo is it an vnſauerye ſawce for the aſſiſtence, to prayſe the meates, or to declare what thei did coſt thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Manerly to diſſemble the foly of other men.</head>
               <p>IF there be any at the table, that through fooliſhenes dooeth anye thing rudely, we muſt rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly diſſemble y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mock thereat.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Libertie at the table.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26127:29"/>
LIbertie muſt be had at the table. It is a vile thing and vitupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as Horace doth ſaie, if a man hath vnwiſely or vnawares ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing at the table to diſcouer and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen it. All that is done or ſaide, muſte be imputed to the wine, to the intente thou heare not the grekes lawe. I hate the geſte that is memoratiue &amp; mynde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To ryſe from the Table whan nature is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied.</head>
               <p>YF the repaſt or diner bee longer than the age of a child requireth, and ſemeth to draw to ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie, by and by if thou haue ſatiſfied &amp; contented nature, withdrawe thy ſelfe either ſecretly, or demaunding and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king leaue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Wyſe moderacion at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnyng of the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the chylde.</head>
               <p>THey that conſtrayne the child to endure and ſuffer hunger, true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after my opinion and mynde thei are fooliſhe, nor thei are not much
<pb facs="tcp:26127:29"/>leſſe fooliſhe that burſte nie vnto the maunger. For as one of theſe maners doth weaken the force of the litle child likewiſe the other doth obfuſcate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite. Ye muſt learne a certain modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the beginning. Ye muſt fede the body of the infant or child with out filling of him entierly: &amp; this muſt be done more oftner than largely.</p>
               <p>There bee that cannot tell whan they bee ful but whan their bellies do ſwel, ſo that they be in daunger to burſte, or to vomite. Thei alſo do hate their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren the whiche notwithſtanding they be yonge and tender, doe let them ſit in a maner all night at the table.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To take awaye his trencher &amp; refuſe, and whan he riſeth from the table to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panye.</head>
               <p>IF than thou muſt ryſe from a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt or diner y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhalbe to lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, take away thy tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cher with the refuſe therof, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt ſaluted him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth the moſt honorable of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> company
<pb facs="tcp:26127:30"/>and afterwards al the other together, go thy wayes: but returne ſhortelye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, to the ende it ſhall not ſeme that thou diddeſt riſe to play, or for ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing not ſo honeſt. Whan thou art returned again, if nede be ſit down or ſtande vprighte before the table re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently, as one that attendeth if ther ſhall be any man that wyll commande thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Wyſedome in ſeruing.</head>
               <p>IF thou ſerue, or doeſt take away beware y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou defile no mannes gowne with anye thynge eyther with brother, or with a caudel, or with any other thyng.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To ſnuffe the candle.</head>
               <p>BEing willing to ſnuffe the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, aryſe firſte from the table, &amp; with thy foote treade vpon that, that thou haſte ſnuffed, that no euil ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer offende the noſe. If thou geue or turne any thing, take hede thou doe it not with the left hande.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:30"/>
               <head>To ſaye grace.</head>
               <p>WHan thou art commaunded to ſaye grace, diſpoſe thy ſelfe as ready whan time ſhall bee to ſaye it, and that euery manne hold his peace. Then thy face muſt be reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and conſtantly turned towards him that ſitteth vppermoſte at the table.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of Metinges and intertayninge.</head>
               <head type="sub">¶ To tourne from the waye, and to geue place and reuerence to perſons worthy of honor: and not to diſprayſe the unknowen.</head>
               <p>YF thou meete with anye man in thy waye the whiche for his age is venerable, or reuerend for his holineſſe or graue for his dignitye, or otherwiſe worthy of honor, looke thou remember to geue him place, to turne thee and to make him waye, puttynge of thy bonet reuerently, and ſomwhat
<pb facs="tcp:26127:31"/>bowing thy knee. That the chylde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſaye thus: what haue I to do with one that I knowe not? what haue I to doe with one that neuer did me good? This honor is not done to man, for his merites and good dedes, but vnto god. God by Salomon hathe ſo commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the whiche hathe commaunded to doe honor, and to ſtande vp before an aged perſon. He hathe alſo commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it by Sainct Paule, to geue double honour to prieſtes: and in briefe, to doe honour to all thoſe to whom honour is due, comprehending alſo the eathnike and painims magiſtrates and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. And if the Turke had dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer vs (that god forbid) we ſhould ſyn yf we ſhould refuſe the honour that is due to ſuche dignitie. I holde my peace at this time of fathers &amp; mothers, vnto whom after and next vnto god, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſte honour is due. And no leſſe is due vnto preceptors and ſcholemaſters, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which as it were doe ingender the ſpirites of men and inſtruct them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Reverence vnto oure egalles.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:31"/>
               <p>FUrthermore this worde of Sainct Paule ought to take place among our egalles, and ſuche as bet lyke vnto vs, preuenting (ſaith he) one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in doyng of honour. He that doth preuent to doe honoure to hym that is like vnto vs, or to our inferior is made neuer the leſſe, but more ciuill, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore more honorable. He muſt ſpeake reverently, &amp; in fewe wordes with hys ſuperious, with his egalles amiablye and gently.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To holde the bonet with the left haude.</head>
               <p>SPeakinge or whan thou dooeſt ſpeake, the left hande muſt hold the bonet, the right hand being or ſwetely lying vpon his nauil, or els the whiche is eſtemed more honeſt, the bonet hanging vpon bothe his handes ioyned together, and the twoo thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes apearing, ſhal couer the vpper part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> girdel. To hold his boke or his bonet vnder his arme holes, is a rude thing. The child muſt haue a certaine ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtnes
<pb facs="tcp:26127:32"/>that muſte geue hym a grace and becom hym, &amp; not to aſtonyſh him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To behold hym peaſably and ſimplye vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſpeak.</head>
               <p>THe eyes oughte to beholde hym vnto whom thou ſpeakeſt, but peaſably and ſimply, ſhewynge no maner of laſciuiouſnes, or of euyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. To holde downe the ſyght, or to looke a toſyde, bryngeth ſuſpicion of an euyll conſcience. To looke a tone ſyde, is like one that willeth and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth euyll. To turne the face hether &amp; thether, is a ſygne of lightnes. It is a foule thinge to chaunge the face into diuers ſorts, ſo that thou wrincle now thy noſe, nowe with thy foreheade, or nowe to lifte vp thy browes, nowe to moue thy lippes, and that thy mouthe be now open, and afterwardes ſhutte. Suche faſhions doe ſhewe a likelihode of a ſpirit like vnto Protheus, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which was wonte to chaunge hym ſelfe into diuers formes. It is alſo a foule thyng
<pb facs="tcp:26127:32"/>to caſt the heere by mouing &amp; ſhaking the head, to cough without neceſſitye, to ſpit, or to ſcratche his head, to digge in his eares to wipe his noſe, to ſcratch his face with his hande, for that dothe reſemble him that wipeth awaye hys ſhamefaſtnes, to rubbe the nape of the necke, and to drawe in the ſhoulders, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which thing we ſee in ſome Italiens.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To ſpeake by ſygnes is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemely for a chylde.</head>
               <p>TO denie in turning the head, or ſhaking it to call another, and to the intent I ſpeake not of all, to ſpeake by ſignes although at ſomtinie it become a man, yet it becommeth not a childe. It is a foule thing to playe w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the armes, to fiddle with the fingers, to ſtand a tipto, and to be ſhorte, not to ſpeake with the tonge, but with al the body, is the propertie of turtle doues, or of faire tailes, and well aprochynge vnto pies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:33"/>
               <head>A ſwete voice, a peaſable, an vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dful, and not to ſpeake to haſtelye.</head>
               <p>THe voice muſt be ſwete and pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, not high, the whiche thing pertaineth to paiſans nor ſo low nor ſo ſoft, that it cannot come to the eares of him that thou doeſt ſpeak vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. That the ſpeche and wordes going before the thought be not to haſtie, but al at leiſure, and ſo that it maie be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded. For if that take not wholy away the naturall brutiſhnes, &amp; a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine impediment of ſpeakinge, yet at the leaſt it doth mitigate and moderate it for the moſt part, conſidering that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brutiſh and to haſty ſpeche hath enge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in many men the vice of the tong, the which nature had not geuen them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Often times to repete the hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable title of hym to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſpeake.</head>
               <p>SPeaking to a man it is a ciuili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie oftentimes to repete his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable title. There is nothing more honorable nor more ſweete than the name of the father and the mother. There is nothing more amiable than the name of a brother and a ſiſter. If
<pb facs="tcp:26127:33"/>thou know not the particuler titles of euery man, all learned men oughte to be honorable maſters. All prieſtes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerende fathers, all that are like vnto thy ſelf brothers &amp; fréndes, to be ſhort, all men vnknowen ſeignours, all wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men vnknowen, danies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Not to ſwere at all, and not to ſpeake fylthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye.</head>
               <p>IT is a vile thinge and an vnho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte to heare an othe oute of the mouthe of a childe, whether it be in ſport or in good earneſt. What is more vile than the cuſtome, whereby in ſome countreis at euery worde, and likewiſe the maidens doe ſwere by the brede, by the wine, and by the candle, and to be ſhort, what is it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ſwere not by? That the childe mingle not his tounge among, and with vile wordes, and that he hearken not vnto them, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally nor to al that, that doth diſcouer and open it ſelfe vnhoneſtly to the eyes of man, and doth preſent it ſelfe vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently to his eares.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26127:34"/>
If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe require that thou muſte name ſome ſhamefull member, thou muſte ſignifye it by ſome modeſtius diſguy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. Furthermore if any thing chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that may trouble the heart, as yf anye men do ſpeake of vomiting, of a iakes, or of a turde, he muſt pray him that it diſpleaſe not his eares.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To gaynſaye with mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and without qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rellyng.</head>
               <p>IF he will gaynſay agaynſt anye thing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he take hede he ſaye not, ye ſaye not truely, ſpecially if he ſpeake to an aged perſon, but firſte to praie him that he will not bee diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſaie: I vnderſtode it otherwiſe of ſuche a man. A wel manered chylde wil neuer quarell with any man, and namely with his equalles, but rather if the thing com to debate ſhall geue it ouer as wonne, or els reporte hym to ſome arbiter or vnpere.</p>
               <p>Not to preferre himſelfe aboue any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor to boaſt himſelfe of anye thing nor blame no other, nor to break no mans pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municacion nor to quarell.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26127:34"/>
THat he preferre not himſelf, nor auaunce himſelf of the thynges that he hath, that he reprehende not the dooinges of other, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he blame not the ſpirite or maners of other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, that he reuele not the ſecretes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men hath tolde him, that he ſet not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes nor ſowe no newe rumours, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he beſpot no mans renoume &amp; name, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he blame not the vice whiche is geuen by nature: for that is not onely iniury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and inhumaine, but alſo foolyſh, as if a would call hym that is blynde, blinde: or a crepil, a crepel: a blincard, a blincarde: a baſtarde, a baſtarde: by theſe meanes it ſhall bee and happen, that he ſhall finde loue without enuy, and frendes lyke vnto hymſelfe. To breake the communicacion of one that ſpeketh, or euer he hath made an end, is an vnciuil and an vnmanerly thing That the chylde take no rancoure or queſtion with any man, that he ſhewe a certaine ſwetenes to euery man, not withſtandinge that he receiue fewe to his enterior and ſecrete familiaritie, &amp; that with great choiſe and eieccion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:35"/>
               <head>Not to reuele and open his ſecretes to any man.</head>
               <p>NOtwithſtanding this, that he neuer tel to any perſon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thing that he would ſhould be kepte cloſe and hidden, for this is but mocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to loke for faith and truſte of ſilence in another, the whiche thou canſte not kepe to thy ſelfe, Certes no man hathe the tong ſo continent, but that he hath ſome man vnto whom he ſheweth his ſecretes. This is a thing moſt ſure, to doe nothing wherof thou mayſte haue ſhame if it be diſcloſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Not to be curious of other mennes doynges.</head>
               <p>BE not very curious of other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s doinges, and if thou haſt ſeen or perceiued anye thinge, make as though y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doeſt not know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. To looke vppon, and with the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of thy eies to beholde the letters, the whiche bee not offered thee, is an vnciuill and an vnmanerly thinge. If anye manne open his coffer and the
<pb facs="tcp:26127:35"/>cheſts of his Iewelles in thy preſence, ſtande backe, for it is an vnmanerlye thing to loke into it, and yet it is more to withdraw or take any thing away. If thou perceiue that there ſhal chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce any ſecrete purpoſe or matter amonge certayne men, drawe backe with oute making of any ſemblaunce, nor medle not with no ſuche purpoſe, wythoute thou be called.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of play. Myrthe in playe without beyng to muche opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiue, &amp; lying.</head>
               <p>IN honeſt playes there muſt be a certaine luſtines and mirthe, ſo there be no ſticking in opinions the whiche is the mother of debates: &amp; that there be no diſceit nor lying: for of theſe ſmal beginninges, come greater iniuries and malice. He gayneth more honeſtly from debate, than he that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth or winneth the thinge trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling himſelfe by debate.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26127:36"/>
Goe not at al againſt the arbiters, nor againſt them that haue iudged y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> game If thou play with thoſe that know not the play, ſo that thou mayſt winne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, ſuffer thy ſelf to winne ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, ſo that the play maye bee more pleaſaunt, and more cherefull. If thou playe with thy inferiours and of leſſe degree than thou thy ſelfe, be ignorant and forgette that thou art of a hyer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree than they are. Men muſte play to refreſh their ſpirites, and not for gain.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>The nature of the chylde is knowen in playe.</head>
               <p>MEn ſay that the nature of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren dothe neuer more appeare than in play. If the ſpiryte and minde of any man be enclined to lie, to noyſe, to anger, to violence, to arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, the vice of nature doth ſhewe it ſelf in play. And therefore that the chylde of good nature be no leſſe lyke hymſelf at play, than at the table.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:36"/>
               <head>¶ Of the chaumber, and of thoſe thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to do ther.</head>
               <head type="sub">To auoide chatteryng and noiſe in the chamber and bedde.</head>
               <p>Silence, ſhamefaſtnes, and alſo ſimplicitie, are praiſed in the chamber: but crying oute, euyl noyſes, and pratling, are not honeſt, &amp; muche leſſe in bed. Whether it be wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou dooeſt vnraye thee, or whan thou doeſt ryſe, remembring ſhamefaſtnes, beware thou diſcouer nothynge to the eyes of other, that both cuſtom and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would it ſhould be couert. If thou haue a common bed with thy compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, be, ſtyll whan thou art laide, and in remouing thy ſelf, vncouer him not nor be not greuous vnto him plucking his couerlet from hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:37"/>
               <head>Praye fyrſte or euer thou ſlepe, and whan thou ryſeſt.</head>
               <p>Or euer thou laye downe thy heade v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the pillowe, make the ſigne of the croſſe vpon thy forehead and breſte, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending thy ſelfe to Ieſu Chriſt, with a litle praier. Doe the ſelfe ſame in the morning whan thou doeſt ryſe, bep in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the daie with praier, for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> canſte not beginne with a better preſage or ſigne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To waſhe his face, his handes, and hys mouthe.</head>
               <p>Aſſoone as thou haſt bene at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, doe nothing vntill thou haſt waſhed thy face, thy handes, and thy mouthe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To bee lyke thy parences in good maners and honeſtye.</head>
               <p>IT is a filthy thing to thoſe that God hath geuen the grace to bee well borne, not to aunſwere and be lyke their parentes in maners and honeſty. Thei who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fortune hathe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:26127:37"/>to be of the common forte of people and lowe borne, and in the countreye, thei muſt the more enforce themſelues to recompence that with elegantneſſe, clenlines, and properties wherewyth fortune hath enuied them. No man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chuſe hymſelf a father, mother, or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey: but yet euery man may forge him ſelf a good minde and good maners. I wil nowe in ſtede of a concluſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a certaine ſmall rule, the which as me thinketh is in a maner worthye of the firſt place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Eaſilye to pardon and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miably to reprehend the faulted of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men.</head>
               <p>THe greateſt parte of ciuilitie is (ſo thou faile not therein) caſily to pardone other mens faultes: nor thou muſt loue thy frend neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, although he haue certain rude ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners and euil fauored condicions: for ther are y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in other perfeccions dooe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence the rudenes of their maners Furthermore we geue not theſe rules as though me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could not be good w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>oute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If thy fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d do fail thorow ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:26127:38"/>in any thyng that ſemeth to bee of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portaunce, it is ciuily done, ſwetelye &amp; ſecretely to moniſh hym. I would that this gifte ſuche as it is, may bee geuen by thee my dere ſonne to all other chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to this ende that by this preſente thou mayſt obtayne and gette thee the loue of thy companions, and that thou cauſe them to haue in recommendacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtudy of liberall artes and good maners. The benignitie of Ieſu Chriſte, keepe and encreaſe continuallye from better to better the noble and good lykelyhoode of vertue that thou repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſte.</p>
               <trailer>The ende of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilitie of child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="instruction">
            <pb facs="tcp:26127:38"/>
            <head>¶ The diſciplyne and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitucion of chyldren.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Howe he muſt ryſe in the Mornyng.</head>
               <head type="sub">Ouid doth ſay, that to watche in the nighte maketh the body, yf it be moyſt. ſubtill.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Herfore aboue al thynges we muſt haue a reſpecie to ſteepe, for feare that it bee not leſſe than reſon requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, or lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger than pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto it. It ſuffiſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a child to haue ſlept ſeuen houres. Then fyrſt of al riſing from thy bed, thou ſhalt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin the day in a good houre, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the father, and of the ſonne, and of the holy ghoſt, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mending thy ſelfe to Ieſu Chriſte with the Lordes prayer. Thou ſhalt geue hym thankes that it hath pleaſed him to geue the this good night. Furthermore thou ſhalte praye hym to geue thee likewyſe all the daye in good proſperitie: leſſe thou fall into ſin. Incontinent after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou be come
<pb facs="tcp:26127:39"/>into the preſence of thy parentes, byd good moro we. Afterwardes combe thy head and waſhe thy handes &amp; thy face, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent thou maiſt goe to ſchole. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> enter in y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> muſt pray Ieſu Chriſt to geue thee his holy ſpirit, conſidryng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whatſoeuer is enterpriſed withoute his aide &amp; help, is wholy vnprofitable. Yet that notwithſtanding leaue not of to ſtudy in the meane while as though he ought not to helpe thee at all w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>oute great labour. Pietie oughte to be the principal point of the child, the whiche is no other thinge but the true ſeruice of god, whiche dothe lye in fayth, loue and in the aſſured hope of god.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of the diligence that ſhoulde be kept in the ſchole.</head>
               <p>HEre with a good minde, &amp; that thou doeſt, let it be done withal thy hart. Anſwer w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> ſhamefaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not euil things bitingly but rather modeſtly. Beware aboue al thinges to be corrected &amp; beaten mery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly. Offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not thy maſter neither in worde nor dede, nor thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions.
<pb facs="tcp:26127:39"/>Be more ready to teach, than to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him that diſputeth againſte thee: make thy hart a Library of Ieſu Chriſt readyng continuallye. Learne from thy childchode holye Scripture. Take alſo a taſke appointed to be red ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily. Nor go not to thy bedde, vntyll thou haue firſt repleniſhed thy ſpirit w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome faire ſentences. If at anye tyme thou haſte lefte oute anye thyng of thy taſke, conbe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne thy ſelf in ſom ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. Learne y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> by certain artes to accuſtome &amp; to geue thy ſelf to thoſe thynges that thou muſt expreſſe. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane whyle y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> muſt rede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſte approued authors. That there paſſe no day that thou get not ſome thing to ware better, for it is a deuiliſhe thyng onelye to ſtudye elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to ware better lerned in ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; not to be better. Trueth it is, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is profitable if vertue gouerne it, ſo that the maners of the oratour be ſuch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſwade, &amp; not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> oracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Theſe be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authors of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> learne elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. Cicero, Terence, Gellius, Quintilian, and Saluſte. Tourne thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> principally we muſt folowe in
<pb facs="tcp:26127:40"/>eloquence, as the firſt to ſpeake well. Neuertheles, I haue perceiued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne dooe diſprayſe Terence, and forbid that he ſhould not be red to chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but they be ſuche that neuer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode Terence wel. Nor I alſo did neuer approue commonly to reade all Poets, and without choſe of them. It is alſo expedient from youth to learne at leaſt way the firſt foundacions of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall ſciences, and likewiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie of ſtories, &amp; to ioine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to tonges.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of the returne and comming from the ſchoole</head>
               <p>BEing come from the ſchole, goe haſtely home without any tary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the waye. And if there be any ſeruice to dooe vnto thy parentes, doe it diligently. But if thou haue ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to repete particularly the thynge that was red thee in the ſchole, doe it, for there is nothing more precious du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this life, than time. Thinke alſo with thy ſelf, that it cannot be recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red agayn, &amp; that it is loſt and paſſeth awaye ſodainlye. Whan the houre of dyner aprocheth, laye the table.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:40"/>
               <head>To prepare to laye the table.</head>
               <p>MAke readye the table at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme accuſtomed: but before thou doe dreſſe it, waſhe diligentlye the glaſſes. Firſt thou muſt laye the table dothe vpon the table, than the Latyn circle, and conſequently the ſalt celler, &amp; finally the bread. As touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, dooe after the cuſtome of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, for in that thing al countreys are variable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>The conſecracion of the table by Sainct Chriſoſtome</head>
               <p>BLeſſed be thou O lorde god, that doeſt fede me from my youthe, &amp; that doeſt nouriſh all creatures, fulfill our heartes with ioy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that we hauinge ſufficientely y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough maie abound in al good works through our ſauior Ieſu Chriſte with whom thou reigneſt in glory, honour, and kingdom with the holy ghoſt tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row oute all worldes. So be it. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt ſay. Our father which art in heauen. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:41"/>
               <head>Another conſecracion.</head>
               <p>HE that through his goodneſſe nouriſheth all thinges, bleſſe &amp; ſanctify all his that is ſet vpon the table, and that that ſhalbe ſet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To take vp the table.</head>
               <p>YE muſt take vp the table eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ye prepared and layde it. Firſt ye muſt take awaye the trenchers, &amp; afterwarde the ſalte ſeller with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſalt, and than the cheſe muſt be taken away before al other thinges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſerue to make an ende of the feaſt and diner, and fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally with bread thou muſt take away the table clothe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Grace after the repaſte.</head>
               <p>GLory be geuen to the Lord, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the holy one, glory to thee, O kynge, for that thou haſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs this refeccion, fyll vs with ioye &amp; gladnes in thy holy ſpirit: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may be found worthy to be receiued into thi preſence, and that we bee not aſhamed and confuſed, when thou ſhalte render to euery one of vs after his workes, ſo be it. Our father whiche art. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:41"/>
               <head>Another grace.</head>
               <p>O Heauenlye father we geue thee thankes that by thy vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble power and might, haſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated all thinges, and doeſt gouerne the vniuerſall worlde by thy wonderfull wyſdom, nouriſhyng and genynge vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure and ſtrength to all creatures tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row thy infinite goodnes, graunt yf it be thy pleaſure to thy infants to drink with thee aboue in thy kyngdome the drink of immortalitie, the whiche thou haſt promiſed and prepared for thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with true hart doe loue the thorow thy ſon Ieſu Chriſt, ſo be it. Our father. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Countenaunce in ſeruing at the table.</head>
               <p>KEpe thy ſelfe vpright wyth thy fete and holdyng them wel toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, take dilygent hede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there lack nothing. And whan thou muſt fil, geue, or ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the table, or take away any thyng, do it honeſtly. Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> muſt do a meſſage in any place, come ſhortly &amp; incontine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly again. Bleſſe god, &amp; ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecracion &amp; grace before &amp; after thy repaſt. And bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany neuer trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but yf thou be queſtioned wat
<pb facs="tcp:26127:42"/>anſwere in fewe wordes. Take hede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thorow obliuiouſnes thou mingle not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pots or cups filling one for another, if there be diuerſitie of wines. Forget not the ſalte, neuer ſet vpon the table the thing that is cutt or broken, whan ye ſhal chaunce to ſuppe by night, be diligent to ſnuffe the candles, that ther enter not into their noſes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſit at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble any euil ſauer. Take hede thou put not out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> candle wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou doeſt ſnuffe it. Accuſtome not thy ſelfe to eate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is taken from the table, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ſet vp in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe. After that grace is ſaid, &amp; that all things be taken away, if thou haue leiſure paſſe thy time at ſome honeſte play w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy companions, vntil that the houre to go to ſchole, do quite thee of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of the countenaunces and good maners that muſt be kept at the table.</head>
               <p>YF it chaunce alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou art ſette at the table, haue this in recorda<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: firſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy nailes be wel parde. Waſh thy handes, kepe thy ſelf vpright. Approue &amp; conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26127:42"/>that thy hoſte doth ſaye that ſpeaketh, Flie al dronkennes. Bee ſober: ſhewe thy ſelf ſo ioyfull and mery, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what is conueniente for thy age, be euermore the laſt of all other to put thy hand in the diſh. If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geue thee a good morſel, refuſe it modeſtly, if thou be enforced take it with geuing of thankes. And whan thou haſt taken alitle pece or porcion therof, geue him the reſt, or to ſome other y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſitteth nexte vnto thee, but yet neuer geue anye thinge to another mans wife y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Nor like wiſe thou ſhalt geue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to any prince or greate Lord. It ſhalbe wel ſuffred to cut &amp; diſtribute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt morſels to thy parentes &amp; frendes. If any man do ſerue thee with any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate thing, as with the liuer of fyſhe, or with any other thynge, thou ſhalte taſte part therof, &amp; diſtribute the reſte. If any man drink vnto the, thank him ioifully, &amp; drink a litle. If thou be not a thirſt, yet at leaſtwaye put the glaſſe to thy mouth. Smile vpon them that ſpeake, &amp; as for thy ſelfe ſpeake not a word, if no man aſke thee any thyng,
<pb facs="tcp:26127:43"/>yf men ſpeake of diſhoneſt purpoſes &amp; thinges, ſmyle not, but turne thy face to ſome other place, aſthough y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> hardeſt nothynge. Striue with no man at the table. Put thy ſelf before no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Boaſt not thy ſelfe of that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in thee. Dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe not other mens things. Be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious &amp; amiable to thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which are of low byrth. Accuſe no man. Be y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> no babler. And ſo doynge y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalte finde laude &amp; prayſe without enuy wyth thy egall frendes. If thou ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy repaſte continue to longe, take thy leaue, &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt ſaluted the aſſiſtence go fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the table. Neuer cut bread agaynſt thy breſt. And cutting it with a knyfe, put not thy litle fyngers vnto it. Gate that, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſette before, or nye vnto thee. And being wyllyng to take ſomewhat that is within the platter, and with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pointe of thy knife, beware thou ſpyll not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meate lyke a hogge vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſelf. Nor meddle not to tourne vp y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> princy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is within the platter, eating of ſoft or poched egges, firſt cut thy brede in ſmall peces, but beware that there fal nothing vpon it. Eate thy egge ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtely,
<pb facs="tcp:26127:43"/>&amp; afterwardes lay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhels whiche are not broke into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> platter. Drink not wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou doeſt eate thine egge, and in eating therof, loke wel vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for moſte part of thy clothyng, leſte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> beſpot the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If thou eate any ſauce, neuer licke thy fingers. Nor as longe as the repaſte, dureth wipe not thy lips nor thy noſe wyth thy ſleue. Nor wype not thy noſe but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an handkercher manerlye &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly. Nor ſpit not rubbing thy ſpittle w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy fingers. Be wel ware that thou put not thy fingers w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſalte ſeller, nor te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauce. Take not to thick, nor to great morſels, but cut the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one after another. Neuer take any thyng out of thy mouth, to laye it agayne vpon thy trencher. Clawe not thy head at the Table. Likewyſe al ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe laughyng and bourdyng at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is filthy. Or euer thou drinke wipe the borders of thy lippes with thy two litle fingers, leſt any man ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greace ſwim within the glaſſes Drink not al ſo hauing yet the morſell in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouthe &amp; before it be ſwalowed downe. It is a rude and a filthy thing to eate &amp; ſpeak together.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26127:44"/>
To ſpit &amp; yawne often, is likewiſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manerly. It is a foolyſhe thynge and a barbarous to leane at the table vppon thy elbowes. Alſo it is a thing worthy to be mocked at, whan one eateth bred to dippe it within the glaſſe in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of people: Lie not vpon thy back. Sup aſmuch as a diſhe can holde. And whan thou doeſt ſup, take good hede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nothing doe fall, and ſup not twiſe at once. Nor ſup not agayne vntill thou haue eaten it, and ſwalowed it. It is for dogges to ſwalowe great morſels, and to gnawe the bones. Beholde not what the aſſiſtence haue before them, nor what thei take &amp; eate. Put not that againe into the platter or diſh, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready hath bene gnawen and bytten. This is a ciuility among Italiens and Frenche men, to caſt there bones and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> refuſe vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> table, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is a filthy thing in Germany &amp; amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Almanes Alſo it is an vnſemely thyng to purge &amp; clenſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teeth with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nailes, or with the tong, or with a knife, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhoulde be done after the repaſt and diner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:44"/>
               <head>Of the thing that ought to be after the repaſt.</head>
               <p>AFter that al be taken away and ſet by, &amp; grace ſaid: he muſt paſſe the time, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time ſuffer him, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> ſome honeſt play, vntill y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> houre &amp; time be com y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou muſt go to ſchole. In the meane whyle find a time to goe to thy leſſon, doing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with al thy might and power that the place requireth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of a perciculer repaſt.</head>
               <p>THy refeccion muſt be te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perate &amp; doone in time and ſeaſon. Dyne largely, and ſup more ſoberlye.</p>
               <p>Take as muche meate as ſhall ſuffice nature, not for pleaſure, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contentacion of the body. After y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſte dynde, doe ſomething ioyfully. Walke a litle before ſupper, &amp; aſmuch after. Study and write faſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To chuſe a ſcholemayſter and to obey hym.</head>
               <p>TAke the beſt learned for a ſcole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter, for it is impoſſible y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he whiche ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing may inſtruct another. Whan thou haſt mette with ſuch a one, by all meanes cauſe hym to beare thee fatherly affecio, &amp; that thou beare vnto him the affeccion of a ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne.
<pb facs="tcp:26127:45"/>For we owe aſmuch honour vnto thoſe that hath taught vs the maner of well lyuing, as to thoſe that haue geuen vs the begynnyng of life. Other waies be thou aſſured thou ſhalt haue a ſcolemai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter in vaine, if likewiſe thou haue him not a true frend. Forthermore be thou continually attentife vnto hym. Learn the beſte thinges euen from the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng and foundacion. It is an extreme foly to lerne thoſe thinges, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> willingly we wyl forget. Hearken not only dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently vnto the maiſter whan he dothe interprete, but alſo very ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly. And be not contente onely to enſue and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe him that diſputeth, but labour if thou maieſt to paſſe him. And to retain the better his good traſes, and meanes of ſpeaking, put them in wrytyng as a treaſure of thy memory. If thou be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, truſt not to thi learned bookes. Forget not the thynges that thou haſt heard aſwel alone and perticularly, as in compani. Deuide the day in houres, by the which thou ſhalt ſtay the thing, that thou ſhouldſt rede. Beyng not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with this, thou ſhalte remembre
<pb facs="tcp:26127:45"/>to geue parte of the tyme, to thy ſecrete thoughtes and contemplacion. The ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>erciſe, whiche is as a certain ſtrife and battell of the ſpirites, doth principall, ſhewe the force of the minde, and doth amake it and augment it. Be not ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the ſtudye of the nyght, and oute of tyme and ſeaſon, for they ſuppe vp and conſume the ſpirit, and are great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye hurtefull to bodely health. But the begynning of the day is frendly to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and proper and meete to ſtudye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>The maner of ſtudying by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphe. Agricola.</head>
               <p>TO order his ſtudy, he muſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally take hede to two thyngs. The fyrſt is, to conſider to what ſtudye thou wylt goe. The ſecond is by what meanes thou maieſt greatly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytte in that, that thou haſt choſen. As touchyng the fyrſt poynt, yf thou haue ſuffyciente goodes, and a competente ſpirit and wyt, I counſell thee to geue thy ſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>all thy force &amp; might, to the beſt ſciences. In the reſt, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt learne
<pb facs="tcp:26127:46"/>the artes of thy childehoode. If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haue red any thing in good authors laboure to tranſlate them into thy mother to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs by proper wordes, and hauing the ſelf ſame ſignificacion, to the ende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whan thou wouldeſt ſaie or write any thing, conferryng by longe uſage thy vulgar tonge with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Latin, thou maiſt pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and commodiouſly expreſſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite of thy minde by that which is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee natural, for to ſpeake Latin af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes more eaſilye. Furthermore yf thou entende to make any thyng, it ſhall be good and mete to forme in thy ſpirite and minde the ſelfe ſame matter in thy mother tonge as largely, and as elegantly as thou maiſt: &amp; afterwardes to pronounce it in Latin purely &amp; with proper ſignificacion, to the intent that all may be ſpoken clerely and largely.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>The ſignes of a good nature.</head>
               <p>TO be not onely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually about and with the maſters, but alſo to ſtudy biſely &amp; dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly. To hafite his companions beyng beſte learned.
<pb facs="tcp:26127:46"/>Alſo wholy to abſtayne from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of thoſe, that menne eſteme to be hurtfull, as well for their maners, as for their renowme. To haue no maner of debate nor ſtrife, but only of letters. To comprehende lightly and to take y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thing that is ſhewed and taughte, and to kepe it faithfully to folow fortunate<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, and to pronounce elega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly. To take hede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in ſpeaking he dooe not precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate his purpoſe, to breake it in hys tonge, to murmure betwene his teeth, but to accuſtome hymſelfe to pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce euery woorde diſtinctly, clerelye, and from point to point. To bee aſhamed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other ſhuld paſſe him, but rather labor to paſſe and excede other. Not to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grye whan he is corrected, &amp; to reioyce whan he is prayſed. To ſtudye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there appeare no fooliſhenes, no diſorder, no vile, nor no ſharp thing in him. Not to haue an vnſhamefaſte forehead, the browes lift vp, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyes bolde &amp; hardy, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tonge affectate, &amp; the viſage iuco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant. Finally y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther be not fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in his face, in his countenance, nor in his goinge, nor ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding vpright, any moleſtious or odious thyng.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:47"/>
               <head>The maner of repeting the leſſon.</head>
               <p>THere bee ſome that labor princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to learne, their leſſon word by worde: but that I like not, for it is a laborious thyng, and in a maner without any fruite or profyt. To what purpoſe is it nedeful to ſaye that word by woorde, that he vnderſtandeth not, as the Popiniay do the. Thou muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continently reade ouer agayne the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that thou haſt hearde, and ſo, that thou deprly doe plante the whole ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in thy mynde. Furthermore thou ſhalt returne agayne to the beginning and begyn to ſearche out euery worde, and onely the thynges that pertayn to grammer, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to wit &amp; know whether there be any verbe of obſcure deriuaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or doubtfull, whether there be any coniugacion he throgleth, how that it maketh in the preterperſitence, what ſupine it hath, what they be of whome it is deriued. What he hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſcende of hym, and what conſtruccion he may haue, what it ſignifieth, and other like
<pb facs="tcp:26127:47"/>thynges. This done, thou ſhalt runne ouer it agayne, ſearchyng principally the thinges that doeth pertayne to the crafte of Rhethorike. If there bee anye good thing, or elegant, and wel ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, note it with a marke, or wyth a lyttle ſtarre. Take good hede to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of verbes, and ſearche the beautifulneſſe of the oracion, fynde the intente of the authour, and by what reaſon he hathe ſpoken euery thyng. Whan thou fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt any thing that doth pleaſe thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware as men ſaye, that thou paſſe not beyonde the loge. Staye thy ſelf, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the reaſon why thou doeſt take ſo great pleaſure in ſuch oracion, &amp; what it ſhould meane y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt not done ſo much in other. Thou ſhalt find y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou waſt moued to do it, for ſom ſubtilite or orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or by ſom harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; to be ſhort, for ſome other reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> find any adage, ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or ſoin olde prouerb, or fable, hiſtory or ſome pleaſant ſimilitude; or as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt think to be ſpoken ſhortlye, ſubtily or wittily kepe it in thy mind, as a treſure for vſe &amp; imitacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. After y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> let it not loth
<pb facs="tcp:26127:48"/>thee at all, to repete it ouer .iiii. times, for the writinges of learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made with a good ſpirit, &amp; with great watch haue this in them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> being redde, and redde agayne a thouſande tymes, they dooe pleaſe more and more, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng dailye newe miracles to thoſe that dailye doe meruall at them. Prayſe not the thyng without a cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commeth cuſtomablye into thy tables, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at other tymes thou haſt not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hede vnto it, the like ſhall chaunce muche more by readyng of good authours. Thou ſhalte reade it therefore foure tymes, and take good hede to that, that may be commodious for Philoſophy, &amp; lykewyſe to Morall Philoſophye, and whether there be any enſaumple y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth to good maners. But is there any thing in this worlde, whereout a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not draw ſom enſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple or ſom figure or occaſion of learning. For we ſhall ſoner ſee the thyng that we ought to doe, than that we ſhould flye and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde, by the goodlye and vile dedes of other. In doing of this thou ſhalt lerne notwithſtanding thou haſt done other
<pb facs="tcp:26127:48"/>thinges. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if it ſeme good vnto the, take payn to learne, for at that preſete thou ſhalt be nothing, or at leaſt waye thou ſhalt be of litle eſtimacion. Ther reſteth no more but to haunt the ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, and to ſet forth thy annotacions, &amp; lykewiſe to vnderſtand other mennes, prayſing the one, and reprehendynge the other, partly defending thy owne, and partlye ſuſſeryng them to bee cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected. Finallye enforce thy ſelfe to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in thy writinges the thynge that thou haſte prayſed to other. Lykewyſe ryſe thou vp after thy leſſon, and walk alone, repeatinge the thing that thou haft red.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>The countenaunces of play and other paſtymes.</head>
               <p>SOmtime we muſt recreate our ſpirites after our ſtudy. Me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe that by plaies &amp; other honeſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes. The honeſt paſtymes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pertain to childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> top &amp; ſcourge, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bowles, the exerciſes of the body, &amp; again te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nis, and leapinges. The ſpices &amp; kindes of leapinge are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leape of graſſehoppers w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> legs, the fete ioyned together
<pb facs="tcp:26127:49"/>and with one legge only. Men doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf with wreſtling, &amp; with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſworde, if it be done in the preſence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maiſter &amp; without enuye. As concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſwimming, better it were to bee a loker on than a doer. But it is much more honeſte to exerciſe his ſpirites w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> inſtrumentes of muſicke, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt honeſt pleaſure, and the moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences to muſes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man can fynd. Playes forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are theſe, diſe, cardes, &amp; other playes of hazarde, to ſwymme in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water with other exerciſes of ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. Theſe be the thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> enryche the playe, grauitie, honeſte myrth, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacitie, vigure of the ſpirit, mutual a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, to playe franklye, to wynne by trueth, and not by diſceit. Alſo to great inſolence dothe diſhonoure the playe, mad cries, foolyſhe countenaunces, to great trouble, and euyll diſceite. It is a goodly thynge to wynne by crafte in honeſt playes, and yf euery man vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antlye defende his place, in the meane while y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hope of a certain ioyful gaine, is cauſe to prouoke ſorn other. For the reſt here are the lawes of playes: that
<pb facs="tcp:26127:49"/>no man ſpeake in his naturall or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers tonge, or in that that is leſſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milier, for in ſo doyng they ſhal learne by playing. This ſhalbe a thyng moſte profitable to recite certayn thynges of the authours ſetting and appoyntyng a certayne price or gaine to the enuye of one and another, ſo that the ſchoole mayſter geue diligente order that they doe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Iduertiſemence for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon aſſemblies and metynges.</head>
               <p>AS oft as any man vnto whome y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doeſt owe honour ſhal ſpeake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, ſtande vp righte, be vnco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, let not thy face be heauy, nor of one ſide, nor ſhameleſſe, nor inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant, but temperate with a ioyfull modeſty, the eyes ſhamefull, and turnynge to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes hym vnto whom thou ſpeakeſt thy fete ioyned, &amp; thy handes together. Wauer not with thy legges, &amp; fyddle not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. Bite not thy lippes, ſcratch not thy hed, nor dig not win thi eares, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thi raime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be honeſtly ordred
<pb facs="tcp:26127:50"/>Cauſe al thy garment, thy vyſage, thy countenaunce, and thy body to ſhew &amp; preſent a ſimple modeſtye, and a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſhamefaſtnes. Be not a folyſh and a haſty babler. That thy ſpirite be not to ſeke, whan he ſpeaketh vnto thee, but be thou attentiue vnto taht he ſpeaketh, if thou muſt aunſwer him do it in few wordes &amp; wiſely. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more doyng hym honoure, name hym now and than by his ſirname, bowing a litle thy knee, likewyſe whan thou haſt ended and finiſhed thy aunſwere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>To flye the company of the euyll.</head>
               <p>THis is a thing that doth ayde &amp; profite very much good noury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng &amp; bryngyng vp, to auoide the company of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euill Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this point Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth admoniſh vs ſaying: my ſonne if the ſinnefull entice thee, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent not vnto them. Take no pleaſure in the way of the euyll. Alſo. S. Paule ſaid, that euil communicacion deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth good maners, a litle leuen deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the hole paſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:50"/>
               <head>How to ſearche the company of honeſt men.</head>
               <p>HAunt not willingly other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany than the company of thy maiſters. Winne through thy obedience and humanitie the beſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and modeſt companions. For it is a thyng that doth profite aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if a man can haue the domeſtycall and familier company of ſtudious and learned men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of the modeſtie that one ought to haue &amp; to hold in walkynge.</head>
               <p>THere be that walk faire &amp; ſoftly enſuing the paſes and ſteppes of thoſe that go to battell, &amp; going, they ſeme to holde and kepe certayne meaſures. Flie as thou wouldeſt flye the peſtilence, ſuche mens ſteppes and paces. Walke not alſo very haſtely, yf no daunger nor no neceſſity require it, nor y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> muſt not go nor walke to ſoftly. There is one kinde or maner of wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng laudable, wherin appereth gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, a wayte of aucthoritie, &amp; a trace of tranquilitie. This is it therefore that thou muſte folowe. So muche there is that thy mouing muſte be pure &amp; ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.
<pb facs="tcp:26127:51"/>A thing coloured, dothe not pleaſe me. For nature muſte forme &amp; faſhion our mocion &amp; goyng. But if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vice in nature, diligence muſte cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte it. If arte do fayle, correccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt ſatiſfye it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of chaſtitie.</head>
               <p>CHaſtitie is next vnto ſhamefaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, nor it cannot be kepte more ſurely than by ſhamefaſtnes, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> induſtrious diligence of the eyes: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſhalt not neede to care to beholde women vnchaſtly &amp; wantonly, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhouldeſt abhorre their ſexe, but to flie &amp; auoid y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euil y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> enſueth thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of garmentes.</head>
               <p>Ameane and comelines is greatly prayſed in garmentes. Thy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell then oughte not to bee to ſumptuous, nor to ſymple and poore, but pertainyng and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like honeſtye, kepe this ſentence of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, in the whiche is ſaide: Let younge minions as comid maidens bee farre from thee for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:51"/>
               <head>Of the entertaynment of the heere.</head>
               <p>AS touchyng this poynt, hearken what S. Paule the Apoſtle ſayth if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> entertain his heere, it is a diſhonour vnto hym, and an honour to the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe that the heere was geuen the woman for a vayle. But a man ſhould not couer his head, becauſe he is the ymage and glory of god.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>An aduertiſement for ciuility &amp; humain conuerſacion.</head>
               <p>FIrſt haue thou an heart y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dothe not fynde that thyng ſharpe and moleſtious that is honeſt, &amp; that doth hys duetie without aſtoniſhment of any feare, or ſodeinly taken by ſome eſperance &amp; hope, acquaint thy ſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the moſt honeſt, trouble not the euyll, prayſe not thy own thynges, reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d nor diſpraiſe not other mens thinges, preferre not thy ſelf aboue other, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though al other ſhuld prefere the, with good men doe pleaſure to the enuious, accuſe no man, be gracious &amp; gentle to thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions which are of low birth, be affable to all men, be merye within the houſe, and wel manered withoute.
<pb facs="tcp:26127:52"/>Declare thy ſecretes to no man, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bryng that the amitie of diuers is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull. Do pleaſure willinglye, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them by conſtrainte. If thou diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe glory, it will folowe thee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou wilt or no, if thou ſeke for it, it will flye from thee. Deſyre not to be praiſed, but doe the thynges worthy of praiſe. Be not acquainted with greate lordes except thei be gracious. Eſteme not to haue any expence more precious than time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of the diſcrecion of ſtudies.</head>
               <p>THe ſpirites of Studentes are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>founded by exceſſiue alteracion but the countinaunce doth dure through meſurable and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie exerciſes, and doth gather together a greater heape than men doe thynke. There is nothing more hurtfull in all thynges than the fulſomenes and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiouſnes that men take, and ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after ſtudy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:26127:52"/>
               <head>Whan thou art retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned home after diner.</head>
               <p>Beynge returned home, do euen ſo as thou dydeſt before dynner Of the thing that ought to be done after ſupper.</p>
               <p>AFter ſupper paſſe thi time with certaine pleaſaunt fables, that done, and after thou haſt bidden thy parentes good night, and al the company, go at a good houre to thy neſt, and there-kneling vpon thy knees reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber with thy ſelfe in what ſtudies thou haſt conſumed the daye. If thou haue done any offence, call for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of Ieſu Chriſt to pardon thee, promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng to bring forth better fruit in time to come. If there bee none, thanke hym of his goodnes, that hath kepie thee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> day from all vice and ſynne. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more thou ſhalt commende thy ſelf vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym with all thy heart, that it wyll pleaſe him to keepe thee from all em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhementes of euill ſpirites, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnhoneſt dreames. That done, enter &amp; goe to thy bedde, reſt thy ſelfe modeſtly in thy ſlepe, lye not vpon thy belly, nor vpon thy backe, but firſt thou ſhalt lye and reſt vpon the right ſide, laying thy
<pb facs="tcp:26127:53"/>armes a croſſe, laying thy right hand vpon the left ſhoulder, and thy left ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vppon thy right ſhoulder.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of the thought that one ſhoulde haue in bed or euer he ſlepe.</head>
               <p>BEfore thou ſlepe thou ſhouldeſt rede ſome exquiſite thynge and worthy of memory, and if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon ſlepe doe take thee, whan thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakeſt, ſerche what that was. Thus muche there is, that thou oughtes to haue this ſentence of Plinie in thy mynde, where it is ſayde, that all the tyme whiche is not employde and ſpente in ſtudye, is loſte.</p>
               <trailer>The ende of the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and inſtituci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of children.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="admonition">
            <pb facs="tcp:26127:53"/>
            <head>An Admonicion to youth to kepe Goddes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes.</head>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Salomon.</head>
               <p>MI ſonne forget not my law, &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten in thy heart my commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, for they ſhal prolong thy lyfe, and thei ſhal gyde the to peace and felicitie. Hange mercy and trueth about thy necke, and thou ſhalt wryte them in the tables of thy heart, &amp; thou ſhalt find grace towardes god, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men with a fortunate prudencye &amp; wiſedom.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>An exhortacion to vertue.</head>
               <p>A Wiſe ſone reioiſeth his father, &amp; a fole is a heuines &amp; a torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to his mother. The treaſures of the euyl ſhal profite nothing, but Iuſtice deliuereth from death. The Lord ſhal not leſe the ſoule of the iuſte through famyne, but he ſhall ouerthrow the embuſhmentes of the euyl. The ydle and ſlouthful ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d bringeth pouerty &amp; the diligent hande enricheth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26127:54"/>
He that ſuſtayneth hymſelfe vppon le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynges, dothe nouriſh the wyndes, and the ſelf dothe folow the flying byrdes. He that gathereth in ſommer is wyſe, and he that ſlepeth in the time of har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt is a childe of confuſion. The bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of god is vpon the head of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſte but iniquitie doth couer the mouthe of the euil. The remembraunce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſt, is bleſſed and praiſed, and the name of the euill ſhal rot and periſh. The wiſe manne ſhall receiue into his heart the commaundementes, but the foole ſhal be puniſhed by his lippes. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſimplye, walketh ſurelye. The mouthe of the iuſt is a vaine of life, but the mouth of the euyll and infidel, ſhal ſtomble through iniquitie, enuye mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſtrife, and charity couereth ſinne. Wiſedom aboundeth in the lippes of the wiſe, and a rod vpon a fooles back. Wiſe men doe hide knowlege, and the mouth of a foole draweth deathe vnto hymſelfe. The worke of the iuſte doth conduit to lyfe, and the fruite of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill is their ſynne.</p>
               <p>To ſuffer correccion leadeth to lyfe, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:26127:54"/>he that myſprayſeth it leadeth himſelf out of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> way. He that is full of wordes is not withoute ſynne, and he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayneth hys tonge, is very prudente &amp; wyſe. The tong of the iuſt is as it wer exquiſite ſiluer, and the heart of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil is vnprofitable. The bleſſing of god maketh men riche. The iuſt are conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually in ioye, and the hope of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull ſhall peryſhe. The mouthe of the iuſt ſhall ſpeake wiſedome, and the euyll tonge ſhall peryſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>An exhortacion of the wyſe.</head>
               <p>CHildren hearken and vnderſtand the diſcipline of the father, to the intent thou mayſt know wiſdom leaue not my lawe, and I wyll geue thee a good gifte, for I alſo haue bene the ſonne of my father, and the moſte tendereſt of my mothers childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the whiche teachyng me ſayde.</p>
               <p>Conuerte not at all to the conſent of ſynners, nor walke not in the way of the euill, but turne awaye, nor goe not
<pb facs="tcp:26127:55"/>by it. Truſt thou with all thy heart in God, and leane not to thy wyſedome.</p>
               <p>Knowe the Lorde whether ſo euer thou go, for ſo it ſhall bee, that he wyll gouerne thy ſteppes. Truſte not at all to thy wyſedome, feare God, and turne thee from the euyl, &amp; from yll. If thou embrace my doctryne, and keepe my commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menie, thou ſhalt liue.</p>
               <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by Iohn Ciſdale, dwellynge in knyghte Kyders ſtrete, nye vnto the Quenes Waredrop.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26127:55"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
